A Guide to the Sister Speak Records, 1998-2019: UA 0015
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Sister Speak Records
1998-2019
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
James Madison University Department of English
Thompson, Mary, Dr.
UA 0015
.66 cubic feet; 2 boxes
The Sister Speak Records, 1998-2019, include administrative files related to Sister Speak, a feminist literary journal and organization at James Madison University, sponsored by JMU's Department of English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
The records were transferred to Special Collections in 2014 and 2016 by Dr. Mary Thompson, Associate Professor of English at JMU. The 2019 Sister Speak Publication Proof was donated by Liz Chenevey in Spring 2020.
Administrative History
Sister Speak: A Feminist Literary Journal is published twice a year at James Madison University. The first issue was printed in the fall semester of 1998, and it originated from English 467: Feminist Literary Theory, taught by Dr. Suzanne Bost, who served as the first advisor to Sister Speak. The first issue consisted of a photocopied collection of students' favorite response papers from this class. While originally titled Sister, Speak, with a comma to indicate a command, later editors dropped the comma in the title. The publication aims to embrace equality between genders, and the goal of Sister Speak is be an amalgam of information that educates about issues related to feminism. To this end, the publication includes works that focus on women and/or gender and that question or challenge oppressive gender roles. As of 2019, Dr. Mary Thompson currently serves as advisor.
Scope and Content
The Sister Speak Records, 1998-2019, consist of .66 cubic feet of material, and document the administrative functions of the publication and organization. Types of materials found within the Sister Speak Records include fliers for informational meetings as well as calls for submissions to the publication. Drafts of magazines consist of clippings from magazines and cut paper glued to single pages, bound into one document with glue. Other materials include zines produced by the JMU Feminist Collective, correspondence, and miscellaneous items including but not limited to one button and unaffiliated feminist publications.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Separated Material
Published (non-proof) issues of Sister Speak were removed from collection and cataloged separately as a periodical in Special Collections.
Index Terms
Subjects:
James Madison University -- Students -- Periodicals; Feminism; Feminist theory; Feminism and literature; Women and literature; Equality; Gender roles
Genre and Form Terms:
Administrative records; Buttons (information artifacts); Drafts (documents); Fanzines; Magazines (periodicals)
- Sister Speak Origins, 1998-2003, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous zines (folder 1 of 2), 2001-2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous zines (folder 2 of 2), 2001-2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Sister Speak Fall 2004, 2004, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Sister Speak Spring 2005, 2004-2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Sister Speak Publication Proof Spring 2005, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Sister Speak Fall 2005, 2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Sister Speak Spring 2006, 2006, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Sister Speak Fall 2006 [contains media], 2006, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Sister Speak Spring 2007, 2007, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Sister Speak Fall 2007, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Sister Speak Publication Proof Spring 2008, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Sister Speak Fall 2008, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Sister Speak Spring 2009, 2009-2010, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Sister Speak 2010, 2010, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Sister Speak Publication Proof, ca. 2010 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Sister Speak Spring 2011, 2011, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Sister Speak Spring 2011 Publication Proof, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Sister Speak Fall 2011, 2011-2012, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Sister Speak Spring 2012 Publication Proof, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Sister Speak Spring 2013, 2013, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Sister Speak Publication Proof, Original Zine - ENG 302/WGSS 300 Fall 2019, 2019 (Box 2, Folder 7)